IU Oral History Archive 1991-1998
Indiana University Libraries
- Merritt, Lynne June 18, 1991, 91-070; 19 pages; 2 audiocassettes, 1 7/8 ips, 68 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  associate dean of college of arts and sciences; associate dean of faculties; chemist; chemistry professor; Research and Advanced Studies dean; Research and Advanced Studies vice president
  Briscoe, Herman T. "Kay"; Gucker, Frank G.; Sutton, Joseph Lee
  1944 GI Bill; analytical chemistry; antimalarials; chemistry; computers; Indiana University computing center; international students; Korean War; student housing; teaching vs. research debate; Vietnam War; World War II; x-rays
- Michael, Marion Bankert October 8, 1996, 96-026; Not transcribed; 3 tapes, 135 minutes; Kraemer, Peter
  Marion Bankert Michael discusses acting, her education at the University of Pennsylvania, feminism, and her association with St. Cloud University in Minnesota. In addition, she recalls Indiana University history from 1971 to 1996, specifically that of the Indiana University Departments of Speech and Theater. Finally, Michael discusses R. Keith Michael and addresses the subject of tenure.
  Indiana University Department of Speech; Indiana University Department of Theater; St. Cloud University; University of Pennsylvania
  Michael, R. Keith
  acting; feminism; tenure
- Michael, R. Keith June 12, 1996, 96-016; 52 pp.; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 147 minutes; index[Number of pages, index; 16 bit/44.1 kbs .wav; Number of minutes-convert hours to minutes-e.g. 1 hour 12 minutes is 72 minutes]; Kraemer, Peter
  R. Keith Michael, professor of theatre, was born on November 16th, 1930 in Muncy, Pennsylvania. He served as the first Chair of the Department of Theatre and Drama from 1971 until his retirement in 1996. Keith discusses his background and education, time in the Navy, and his arrival at Indiana University in 1971. Also, he talks about the changes made in the Department of Theatre and Drama under his tenure as Chair. He discusses fundraising for the department and staffing issues encountered while he served as Chair. Lastly, he recalls his memories of teaching and discusses his retirement.
  Barter Theater; Booth Theater; Brown County Playhouse; Department of Theatre; Indiana University of Pennsylvania
  Europe; Indianapolis, Indiana; Muncy, Pennsylvania
  chair; theatre professor
  Heppner, Hubert; Michael, Marion; Norvelle, Lee; Porterfield, Robert
  acting; directing; fundraising; Great Depression; Korean War; student life; teaching
- Miller, Jeanne S. November 16, 1993, 91-218; 15 pages; 1 audiocassette, 1 7/8 ips, 47 minutes; index
  Jeanne Miller attended Indiana University from 1943 to 1948. After her undergraduate studies she attended the Law School in Bloomington, graduating in 1948. In 1971 she was appointed to the Indiana University Board of Trustees, serving until 1974. In this interview she discusses campus and Bloomington during World War II, her experience as a female student in law school, her appointment to the Board of Trustees, and her experiences since.
  Board of Trustees; Maurer School of Law
  Fort Wayne, Indiana; New Haven, Indiana
  attorney; lawyer
  Ryan, John W.
  Board of Trustees; female law students; G.I. Bill; gender roles; law school; Mini University
- Miller, Thomas M. November 12, 1993, 91-219; 11 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 13 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Thomas M. Miller, born on March 2, 1930, was a student at Indiana University in the late nineteen forties who went on to a long and successful career in the area of banking. In this interview, he speaks of his days as a student, placing particular emphasis on the presence of veterans on campus and the impact of the Korean War. Actively involved with the activities of the Indiana University Foundation, Miller discusses funding issues and his ideas about the faculty research debate.
  academic research; Korean War; student funding; World War II veterans
- Miller Steven A.October 18, 1993, 91-210; 18 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7'8 ips, 40 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Stevan A. Miller, born in Indianapolis in 1948, was a student at Indiana University from 1966- 1970. He served as Treasurer for the University in 1990. He recounts his experience at the university in the 1960s, the anti-war protests on campus, and his time in the MBA program. Lastly, he touches on the changing relationship between the city of Bloomington and the university from the 1960s to the 1990s.
  Indiana Univeristy Foundation; IUPUI; ROTC; Upjohn Company
  Detroit, Michigan; Vietnam
  treasurer
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.
  MBA program; student attitudes; student protests; Vietnam War; Vietnam War protests
- Millisen, Robert May 8, 1996, 96-009; 35 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Robert Millisen came to Indiana University in 1937 as a professor and later administrator in the speech pathology division of the Department of Speech. Prior to this, Millisen discusses his experiences at Creighton College, Simpson College in Iowa, and the University of Iowa. He also speaks of the Great Depression, his father's career as a railroad engineer, and how he entered the field of speech pathology. In addition, he recalls the creation of a speech pathology residence clinic at Indiana University, and the dedication and funding provided by the sorority, Psi Iota Xi, for the creation of speech services for handicapped children in the state of Indiana.
  Creighton College; Psi Iota Xi; Simpson College; University of Iowa
  speech pathology professor
  Briscoe, Herman T. "Kay"; Johnson, Wendell; Norvelle, Lee
  Great Depression; railroad engineers; speech pathology; speech pathology residence clinic
- Mitchell, Frederick Pence October 6, 1993, 91-202; 14 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Frederick Mitchell, born on November 20, 1926, began his education at Indiana University in 1948 and received his undergraduate degree in 1953 after two interruptions for United States military service in the Merchant Marines and the army, respectively. A former student body president, he was actively involved in campus life through student government, and membership in his fraternity, Sigma Nu, and the Sphinx Club. In addition, Mitchell discusses the impact of veterans, the Korean War, World War II, and hazing on Indiana University. He also speaks briefly of his relationship with Herman B Wells.
  Sigma Nu; Sphinx Club
  fraternities; fraternity hazing; Korean War; student government; World War II; World War II veterans
- Mitchell, Thomas J. May 1, 1992, 91-099; 13 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on October 21, 1922, Thomas J. Mitchell is a 1949 alumnus of Indiana University who began studying at the university in 1942. After serving three years in the United States Air Force during World War II, he returned to Indiana University in 1946 to complete his undergraduate degree. In this interview, Mitchell discusses his days as a student at Indiana University and makes comparisons to his children's experiences at the university thirty years later. In addition, he speaks of the changes that Indiana University has undergone, the effects of World War II, transportation, and athletics at Indiana University. He also discusses his successful career as an insurance agent and how his education and experiences at Indiana University helped him to achieve occupational success.
  insurance agent
  Indiana University athletics; transportation; university growth; World War II
- Mohr, William H. April 15, 1992, 91-093; 22 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 82 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  William H. Mohr, a alumnus of Indiana University at Bloomington of the class of 1979, went on to attend and receive his medical degree from the Indiana University School of Medicine at Indianapolis in 1983. Extremely involved in student government, he was a member of the student athletic board and the Board of Aeons. In addition, he held the student trusteeship position on the Indiana University board of trustees for one term. Mohr recalls his memories of his student days at Indiana University at Bloomington and the summer courses he took at Indiana University at Kokomo. Several people exerted considerable influence on Mohr during these years including Eugene Cortis, Steve Halkovich, and George Pinnell.
  Board of Aeons; board of trustees; Indiana University Kokomo; Indiana University School of Medicine; Indiana University Student Athletic Board
  Cortis, Eugene; Halkovich, Steve; Pinnell, George
  student trusteeship
- Morrow, Joseph T.June 16, 1994, 91-273; 10pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 18 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Joseph Morrow was born in Huntington Indiana on December 6, 1930. He attended Indiana University starting in a1954 for undergraduate and law school. He discusses his time working as a law clerk for Judge Luther Swygert after law school, his tenure at a law firm in Hammond, Indiana, and his career change into the banking business. Morrow recounts his time on campus during the civil rights era, changes on campus and in Bloomington, as well as his time serving on the IU Foundation Board.
  Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University Foundation Board; Indiana University Law School; Varsity Club
  Fort Wayne, Indiana; Hammond, Indiana; Huntington, Indiana
  law clerk; lawyer
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Ryan, John W.; Swygert, Luther
  business education; campus changes; civil rights; law school; student attitudes
- Mosbacher, GeorgetteOctober 7, 1993, 91-207; 19 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 48 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Georgette Mosbacher was born January 16, 1947 in Hammond, Indiana. She attended Indiana University from 1965-1969 graduating with a degree in radio and television. After college, she moved back to Highland, IN before moving to California to start a career as an entrepreneur. Finding success in her business, she went on to become an author and political advisor serving on the Republican Party Executive Council and the Advisory Commission on Trade and International Negotiations under President George Bush and President Bill Clinton. She discusses her experience as a student and her time on the Indiana University Foundation Board.
  Center for Strategic and International Studies; Indiana University Foundation; Indiana University Foundation Board; Republican Party
  California; East Chicago, Indiana; Hammond, Indiana; Highland, Indiana; Washington, DC
  chief executive officer; entreprenuer; student teacher
  Bush, George, Sr.; Clinton, Bill
  business; entrepreneurship; female students; NAFTA; politics; Republicans; women in politics
- Motherwell, JosephJuly 16, 1992, 91-124; 21 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 79 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Joseph R Motherwell, born November 6, 1958 in Fort Wayne, Indiana, attended Indiana University- Fort Wayne from 1979- 1987. While working full-time for Nipsco utlity company of Northern Indiana, Motherwell attended class over an 8 year period, the last two of which he served in student government. After graduating from Indiana University Fort Wayne, he attended law school on the Indianapolis campus from 1988- 1991. In this interview, Motherwell discusses what it was like working full-time and going to school, his time serving in student government, and his tenure as a member of the Board of Trustees. Lastly, Motherwell discusses his career plans after graduating from law school.
  Board of Trustees; Indiana University Fort Wayne; Indiana University School of Law
  Fort Wayne, Indiana; Indianapolis, Indiana
  laboer; lawyer
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Knight, Bob
  Indiana University regional campuses; student government
- Mulholland, John Dowsley "Jack" July 29, 1991, 91-072; 18 pages; 1 cassette, 1 7/8 ips, 51 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  John Dowsley "Jack" Mulholland was born in Rochester, New York in 1927. He describes his career in the corporate world, during which time he moved to Evansville, Indiana. After three years there, he was recruited by Indiana University to come to Bloomington. There, he held the positions of assistant vice president of financial affairs and treasurer between 1972 and 1992. Mulholland also taught accounting and worked with community and alumni groups. He reflects upon the reputation and purpose of Indiana University and the role of higher education in general.
  Bloomington Community Foundation; board of trustees; Bristol-Myers; Mead Johnson and Company; National Association of College and University Business Officers
  accountant; accounting professor; comptroller; university treasurer; university vice president
  Clapacs, Terry; Pinnell, George; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  Bloomington, Indiana; Evansville, Indiana
- Nakhnikian, George February 2, 1997, 96-033; 32 pages; 2 tapes; index; Kraemer, Peter
  Open; tapes permanently sealed
  Born on November 12, 1920, George Nakhnikian joined the Indiana University faculty as a member of the Philosophy Department in 1968 and served there until his retirement in 1988. In this interview, he recalls his childhood as an Armenian in Bulgaria and his immigration to the United States. Nakhnikian also discusses his participation in World War II, his use of the GI Bill to complete graduate school and his quick rise to chairmanship of the Department of Philosophy at Wayne State University. In addition, he recalls his undergraduate years at Harvard University and his coming to the Indiana University Department of Philosophy. Nakhnikian discusses departmental tensions, his years as chair, and the growth of the department.
  Harvard University; Indiana University Department of Philosophy; Wayne State University
  Dunn, Mike; Eisenberg, Paul
  Bulgaria
  1944 GI Bill; Armenian oppression; philosophy; World War II
- Nash, John Arthur July 17, 1992, 91-127; 17 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 54 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born in 1938, John A. Nash is a 1960 Indiana University alumnus who went on to earn his MBA from the Indiana University School of Business. After serving a year and a half in the United States army, Nash went on to a long and successful career in finance. In this interview, he recalls his years as a student at Indiana University including campus life, minority students, and his involvement in campus politics which culminated in his election to the presidency of the student body. Nash speaks of his participation in the Little United Nations Assembly, or LUNA, during his undergraduate years. In the years after graduation, he became involved in the Indiana University alumni association and Hoosiers for Higher Education. He recalls the assassination of president John F. Kennedy and cites his views of the regional campus system at Indiana University. He was influenced by Byrum Carter, John Mee, and Herman B Wells.
  Hoosiers for Higher Education; Indiana University Alumni Association; Little United Nations Assembly
  Carter, Byrum; Mee, John; Wells, Herman B
  campus politics; Indiana University regional campuses; John F. Kennedy assassination; minority students; student life; student presidency
- Nelms, Charlie December 1, 1993, 91-224; 21 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 60 minutes; index, 1 VHS; Freedman, Jean
  Born on September 11, 1946, Charlie Nelms earned his graduate degree from Indiana University in 1971 and completed his doctorate at the university in 1976. After working at the Indiana University Northwest campus for several years and at several other college positions in other states, Nelms returned to Indiana in 1987 to serve as chancellor of Indiana University East. In this interview, he speaks of his years as an Indiana University student, African-American students, experiences of racism, and his development of the Foster Quad Black Student Association. In addition, he speaks of his work at the City University of New York, its experimental open admission system, and the importance of the Indiana University Indiana University regional campuses. Finally, Nelms discusses the financial problems facing higher education, the teaching vs. research debate, and his proposed resolutions to these problems.
  City University of New York; Foster Quad Black Student Association; Indiana University East; Indiana University Northwest
  Greenley, Betty
  African-Americans; faculty pensions; Indiana University regional campuses; open admissions system; racism; teaching vs. research debate; university funding
- Nicholson, Edward A. June 2, 1994, 91-266; 14 pages; 1 tape, 42 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born on April 25, 1940, Edward A. Nicholson discusses his work at Indiana University, specifically at Indiana University-Purdue University Fort Wayne, or IPFW. At IPFW, he served first as vice chancellor, and then chancellor of that regional campus. In this interview, he discusses the difficulties and complications that arose due to the fact that IPFW was under the joint control of Indiana University and Purdue University. He speaks of the different philosophies and policies of each of these universities and the implications for IPFW. In addition, Nicholson discusses the strengths and many positive aspects of the Fort Wayne campus and the influence of specific university presidential administrations, especially that of John Ryan at Indiana University.
  Indiana University-Purdue University Fort Wayne; Purdue University
  Indiana University regional campuses
- O'Neil, Robert M. May 24, 1994, 91-263; 19 pages; 1 tape, 56 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Born on October 16, 1934, Robert M. O'Neil discusses his close early connections to and similarity with Thomas Ehrlich. O'Neil eventually served as the vice president of Indiana University from 1975 to 1980, and then continued into a long and successful career as an administrator and law professor. In this interview, O'Neil speaks of his years at Indiana University and the issues of capped enrollment in the School of Business, minority students, and the continuing academic strength across many disciplines at Indiana University. In addition, he speaks of John Ryan and shares a few interesting stories of Herman B Wells.
  law professor; university administrator
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Remak, Henry H.H.; Ryan, John W.; Wells, Herman B
  campus controversy; curriculum strengths; enrollment; minority students
- Orescanin, Danilo May 23, 1991, 91-063; 32 pages; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 97 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Danilo Orescanin completed his Master's degree at Indiana University in 1954 and his doctorate in 1960 in the area of business administration. He went on to a long and successful career which included both teaching and administration at the university level. For example, Orescanin was assistant to the president under Joseph Sutton, vice president for university relations, and many other high-level administrative posts, some of which took him to four of Indiana University's regional campuses. In addition, he continued to teach intermittently and, toward the end of his career, focused solely on teaching in Indiana University's School of Business. In this interview, Orescanin discusses his role in setting up a School of Business at the University of Dacca in Bangladesh through Indiana University, his philosophies of education, different Indiana University presidential administrations, and campus changes.
  Indiana University Northwest; Indiana University School of Business; Indiana University School of Music; Indiana University Southeast; IUPUI
  business professor; university administrator
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Kerr, Clark; Laird, Byron; Mee, John; Porter, John; Ryan, John W.; Stahr, Elvis J.; Sutton, Joseph Lee; Weimar, Arthur M.; Wells, Herman B
  Bangladesh
  campus changes; campus controversy; curriculum; education philosophy; South African investments
- Pozzatti, Rudy October 4, 1996 October 14, 1996, 96-025; 73 pp.; 4 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 235 minutes; index; interviewee's CV; copy of Rudy Pozzatti: American Printmaker; Kraemer, Peter
  Rudy Pozzatti, born on January 14, 1925 in Telluride, Colorado was a professor of fine arts starting in 1956. He discusses his experience in World War II with the 659th Field Artillery Battalion, his education at University of Colorado, Boulder, and coming to Indiana University in 1956. Further, he discusses his printmaking, development of the printmaking program, sculpture, his work with students, and his current projects.
  Echo Press; Guggenheim Foundation; National Endowment for the Arts; University of Colorado, Boulder; University of Nebraska
  Boulder, Colorado; Florence, Italy; Germany; Italy; Nebraska; Silverton, Colorado
  painter; printmaker; art professor; sculptor
  Annon, Charles; Bain, Wilfred; Beckmann, Max; Black, Wendell; Bowie, Theodore; Lowe, Marvin; Megrew, Alden; Pozzatti, Dorothy; Shahn, Ben; Smith, Henry; Wolle, Muriel
  art; art history; art materials; GI Bill; Italian Americans; painting; printmaking; religion; sculpture; student attitudes; World War II; World War II experiences; World War II veterans
- Palmer, JudithDecember 6, 1993July 20, 1994, 91-228; 39 pp.; 3 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 122 minutes; index[Number of pages, index; 16 bit/44.1 kbs .wav; Number of minutes-convert hours to minutes-e.g. 1 hour 12 minutes is 72 minutes]; Freedman, Jean
  Judith Palmer, born April 2, 1948 in Washington, IN, is an Indiana University Bloomington Alumni and attended Indianapolis Law School from 1968-1973. While attending school Palmer worked in state budget agency. She served as executive assistant to Govern Otis Bowen from 1977 to 1981. Palmer eventually ended up back at IU as special assistant to President John Ryan. In this interview she discusses Indiana University in the 1960s, IU Law School, her time in state government, and changes IU has undergone since the 1960s.
  McKinney School of Law
  Indianapolis, Indiana; Washington, Indiana
  governor's staff; state budget director
  Bowen, Otis; Ehrlich, Thomas; Kessler, Jim; Ryan, John
  academics; Civil Rights Movement; law school; non-traditional students; state government; student attitudes; student protests
- Parrish, SusanNovember 15, 1993, 91-220; 15 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 45 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Susan Parrish, born in Marrietta, GA in 1947, served as Secretary of the Board of Trustees for Indiana University. In this interview she discusses her experience with the Peace Corps in pre-revolution Ethiopia, her education at West Georgia College, and her arrival in Bloomington in 1976. She also discusses her experiece as Secretary of the Board of Trustees, and speculates on what the financial crisis of the 1990s meant for Indiana University.
  Board of Trustees; West Georgia College; Peace Corps
  Ethiopia; Fort Wayne, Indiana; Marietta, Georgia
  adminstrative assistant; secretary
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Shirley, Janet
  Peace Corps
- Pebworth, RobertSeptember 25, 1991, 91-078; 16 pp.; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 75 minutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  Robert Pebworth attended Indiana University Bloomington from 1927-1932, serving as editor of the Daily Student newspaper. He discusses the atmosphere during this time and his involvement with the university band and its development as the Marching Hundred, Also, he discusses his tenure as President of the Alumni Association in 1957.
  Alumni Association; Bloomington World; Indiana Daily Student; Marching Hundred; Union Board
  alumni secretary; editor
  Bryan, William; Carmichael, Hoagy; Cravens, John; Kinsey, Alfred; Pyle, Ernie
  journalism; kinsey research; marching band; student attitudes
- Popoff, FrankApril 20, 1994, 91-249; 11 pp.; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 mminutes; index; Freedman, Jean
  dean's advisory committee; Dow Chemical Company; Indiana University Foundation
  Midland, Michigan; Sofia, Bulgaria; Terre Haute, Indiana
  chairman; chief executive officer
  Ehrlich, Thomas; Mee, John; Mueller, Joseph; Ottison, Skyler; Rau, John; Wenworth, Jack